<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Royal general, or, The Camp at Putney Heath to the tune of State and ambition &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33556</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13523245</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13523245</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99931</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99931)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1556:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Royal general, or, The Camp at Putney Heath to the tune of State and ambition &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Dean ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:99931:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>The ROYAL GENERAL Or the <hi>Camp</hi> at PUTNEY HEATH</head>
            <opener>To the <hi>Tune</hi> of <hi>State and Ambition</hi> &amp;c.</opener>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw the great <hi>Monarch</hi> of <hi>England's</hi> bright Splendor,</l>
               <l>doth ſhine over <hi>Europe</hi> like <hi>Jove</hi> in his <hi>Throne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Makes <hi>France</hi> to the <hi>Empire,</hi> &amp; <hi>Spanierd</hi> ſurrender,</l>
               <l>The peace and the plenty of what is their own;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Turk</hi> and the <hi>Teiklites</hi> thereby are o're powerd</l>
               <l>And cruſht <hi>by the conduct of Chriſtians ſtrong Arms,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such ſucceſsful bleſſing the heavens have ſhowred,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Turks</hi> and the <hi>Tartars</hi> are loſt in the <hi>Storms.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Charles</hi> and his <hi>Highneſs</hi> they bravly have Conquer'd</l>
               <l>Our pretended <hi>Proteſtant Turks</hi> of the Race,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Haſlrig, Bradſhaw</hi> and <hi>Tapskie</hi> who Scamper'd,</l>
               <l>And left his deſciples to hang in diſgrace:</l>
               <l>With pollitick prudence and mercy they've turned</l>
               <l>The Sceam of the Kingdom as it was before,</l>
               <l>The ſaucy proud <hi>Presbyter</hi> formerly ſcorned,</l>
               <l>Are fore't to their Sovereign to whine and adore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>Come brave daring <hi>Tories</hi> that's warlike affected,</l>
               <l>O'th offspring of <hi>Mars</hi> and delights in a Drum;</l>
               <l>At which the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> are vex't and affrighted;</l>
               <l>Where none but Heroick brave ſouls are to come:</l>
               <l>At <hi>Putney</hi> you'l ſee his brave <hi>Highneſs reſtored</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chief General by <hi>Land</hi> as well as by <hi>Sea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Merits deſerving the god's have implored,</l>
               <l>That none but the right in ſucceſſion ſhou'd ſway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Chalres</hi> more than <hi>Ceſar</hi> an Army hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</l>
               <l>To protect his Friends, and keep Rebells in awe,</l>
               <l>Not to be disbantled at <hi>Parliament</hi> pleaſure;</l>
               <l>Wee'l make thoſe damd'd hot-ſpurs Alegeance to <hi>know;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Hoboys</hi> and <hi>trumpets</hi> ſounds tan, ta, ra, ra, ra</l>
               <l>The Colours do floriſh Drums beat dub, a dub</l>
               <l>Each loyal Commander his Souldiers doth cheriſt</l>
               <l>They'le make <hi>Jack Presbyter fly from</hi> his tub.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>No <hi>Theatre, Opera</hi> nor garden of pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Can equal the harmony of <hi>Engliſh Camp;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Three Kingdom's <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>Monarchs</hi> chief Treaſure,</l>
               <l>A terror to our Engliſh Turks o'th' ſame <hi>ſtamp</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our <hi>New-Caſtl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Rebells and Scotch apprehended,</l>
               <l>Muſt lay by their hopes of raſing the Croude;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rumbold</hi> now taken ſhall be recommended,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Argile</hi> on Gibbet as high as a Cloud.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>The Guards and Malitia in real Emulation,</l>
               <l>Each Souldier deſerving Commiſſioners place;</l>
               <l>Their ſouls are aſpir'd above Elevation,</l>
               <l>And e'ry Commander <hi>Achilles</hi>'s grace:</l>
               <l>The King &amp; the Duke &amp; Prince are Triumphant,</l>
               <l>With loud Acclamations, and Trophies of joys,</l>
               <l>To ſee <hi>proud oppoſers</hi> ſubdu'd that were <hi>Rampant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With huzza's let's drink their health <hi>Tory-Boys.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>All that in war-like Diſciplin delighteth,</l>
               <l>Pray for the ſucceſs of the Chriſtians Arms,</l>
               <l>And for all that contribut's to pay <hi>thoſe that fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In the Holy Wars &amp; their Duty performs;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thoſe that diſcover'd</hi> the laſt <hi>Plot</hi> in <hi>Scotlland,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wherein <hi>Sterling-Caſtle</hi> was to be ſurpris'd;</l>
               <l>And for the perſervation of peace in old <hi>England;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And let thoſe be hang'd that trims in diſguiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Dean,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Cranborn-Street</hi> near <hi>Newport-Houſe</hi> in                         <hi>Leiceſterfields,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
